very good and welcome one more day to
betatech for those of you who are new to the
channel here we talk about software and
technology and specifically in this series
we talk about design patterns we are going
to explain one by one each pattern looking at
their uses and explaining them with
examples but if you still don't know what
a design pattern is I'll leave the index of
the series up here and also in the
description so you can take a look and
today we are going to talk about the composite pattern
it is a very useful pattern and it is used
a lot when developing
graphic environments or video games since it
greatly simplifies the way of thinking about
three-dimensional scenes if you are even a
little bit familiar with Unity you will know
that each element of the game is what is
known as an entity or a Game object
the character the enemies the stage
each element of the game is an entity
each one with its own properties and
a very useful thing that Unity allows you to do
is nest these entities within
others give them a hierarchy you can
have the character as an entity and
below it have child entities such as
weapons or other elements
related to the character this
allows you to transfer the
transformations from the parent to
For example, you can move the children in
relation to the parent, the composite pattern is
precisely one of the possible
solutions to implement this
behavior, it basically consists of
having a generic data type from which
other elements of the same type can hang,
basically, it is about setting up a
tree-shaped hierarchy so
that each entity can be made up of
other entities of the same type, which in
turn can be made up of other entities of the same
type, which in turn can be made up of other entities of the same type, which in turn can be made up of other entities of the same type, which in
turn
can be made up of other
entities of the same type, you understand what I mean, it
is, in short, a recursive structure.
But before going into detail about how
this pattern is specifically used,
let me thank the
sponsor of this video. arc arc is
a platform designed for
developers who are looking for
remote work. They have a
web scraping platform that is
constantly looking for the best
remote offers on different portals and
allows you to compare the different
offers so that you can apply to the ones that
best fit you. In addition, with arc, you
can answer some small quizzes
to demonstrate your skills as a
programmer and in this way you can
skip certain stages in the
selection processes, such as some
technical interviews, since  in the end ark
itself validates your knowledge and in case that
wasn't enough they
also have a community a
community that will allow you to share
experiences and resolve doubts about
remote work I want to thank ar for
reigning this video and if you want to know more I'll
leave the link in the description and in
the pinned comment you know that
right now I'm working remotely and
therefore when
opportunities like this appear that
may also be useful to you I like to
share them and without much further ado let's continue
with the video well let's go now
to the example of the video game imagine that
each entity has a
rendering function which
basically draws the entity on the
screen renders it either in three
dimensions or in two dimensions now
we think that what we want to implement
is a very large enemy type these
enemies are not that are made up of
several parts such as the torso
and the limbs and each part has
a different logic we can
then think of that the enemy is a set
of pieces or a set of smaller enemies
as I say it can have the
main body and a left leg that throws
fire and a right leg that throws
poisoned water each piece with its logic The
example  specifically it doesn't matter much but
in the end the thing is that at the
code level we don't want to
always have to carry all the objects
separately with us or have to
call the functions of each
individual part every time we want to do
something every time we want to move the
enemy we have to move all its
parts what we want to do is to be able to
call a general function and have it
be in charge of transmitting it to its
children in the case of the render we
want to render the big enemy we don't
want to render each part
separately for this we can implement
precisely the composite pattern creating
an entity called big enemy that
is formed within it by
different smaller entities in
this way as the big enemy is in
itself already an entity we can use it
as if it were a simple entity
one more entity within the set of
entities that we have and the system
from the outside does not need to know nor should
know that it is a
composite entity it will be the responsibility of the
parent entity to manage the logic and
the functions of the child entities in
my case I used precisely
this pattern for the first time in the
video game subject to make an enemy that
was basically an octopus the octopus had
a tentacle with several spheres worth
each  sphere was an entity that could
kill the player and the player had to
kill each of these spheres
individually before being able to face the
octopus so each of these spheres
individually were a
simple entity they had no children but
they were all part of the parent entity of
the octopus therefore we as
developers could move the octopus
freely since the spheres always went
with it in addition this structure allows
the children to behave
differently depending on the properties
of the parent we could make the
rest of the spheres increase the speed
when the octopus sees that it has less
spheres alive because each one goes
faster or each one is bigger you
can do a thousand tricks but the
important thing is that all this logic
resides in the octopus for the
external system the octopus is the octopus it does not matter
if it has 5, 20 or 30 spheres anyway
changing a bit of the subject of
octopuses and the sea the uml diagram of this
pattern is quite simple since in the
end everything inherits from the same thing in our
case we would have the
entity abstraction and the concrete class the class that
inherits or that implements this entity is
the  octopus then we would also have another
concrete class which would be the Sphere which
is also obviously a daughter or an
implementation of the entity class the
octopus because it has as property a
set of entities which in this case are
going to be our spheres obviously and
therefore every time the octopus
executes a function of any type it
can also process the
corresponding message to its children without a doubt it
is one of the patterns that I like the most
on a personal level since in addition to being
very easy to understand it provides a lot of
flexibility it allows you to generate
super clean code since in the end it is an
extraction that unifies the behavior
of all your entities in a very
simple and very clear way to use and as
usual I hope you liked this video
without much more we will see you in
the next one until another